Get ready for rush hour.
Speed is a action, thriller film directed by Jan de Bont.
Tensions run high when a crazed bomber rigs a Los Angeles bus with a device that will kill
everyone on board if the vehicle's speed dips below fifty miles per hour.
Jack Traven, played by Keanu Reeves.
Howard Payne, played by Dennis Hopper.
Annie, played by Sandra Bullock.
Capt. McMahon, played by Joe Morton.
Harry, played by Jeff Daniels.
Stephens, played by Alan Ruck.
Speed is a 1994 American action thriller film directed by Jan de Bont in
his feature directorial debut, and written by Graham Yost.
Keanu Reeves, Dennis Hopper, and Sandra Bullock star in the film,
alongside Joe Morton and Jeff Daniels in supporting roles.
The plot centers on a city bus rigged by a vengeful extortionist Howard Payne
(Hopper) to explode if its speed drops below 50 miles per hour (80 km/h).
Reeves plays LAPD officer Jack Traven, who is tasked with preventing the disaster, with
Bullock portraying a passenger who becomes unexpectedly involved in the mission.
The film was inspired by both Runaway Train and the 1975 Japanese
language action thriller film The Bullet Train.
Screenwriter Graham Yost was told by his father, Canadian television host Elwy Yost, about a 1985 film
called Runaway Train starring Jon Voight, about a train that speeds out of control.
Elwy mistakenly believed that the train's situation was due to a bomb on
board: such a theme had in fact been used in The Bullet Train.
After seeing the Voight film, Graham decided that it would have been better if there had been a bomb on
board a bus with the bus being forced to travel at 20 mph to prevent an actual explosion.
A friend suggested that this be increased to 50 mph.
Speed premiered on June 7, 1994, and was released on
June 10, 1994, by 20th Century Fox.
The film was a sleeper hit, receiving positive reviews from critics and grossing $350 million
worldwide against a $30–37 million budget, becoming the fifth-highest-grossing film of 1994.
At the 67th Academy Awards, Speed won Best Sound.
The film also won Best Sound and Best Editing at the
48th British Academy Film Awards.
A sequel, Speed 2: Cruise Control, was released on June 13, 1997, but performed poorly and was critically
lambasted, receiving widespread criticism for Reeves's absence and the film's change in setting.
The film explores themes of s.w.a.t., bomber, bus bomb,
los angeles, california, falling elevator.
The tone is intense.